<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="windows-1252" standalone="no"?>
<operatorHelp lang="en_EN">
	<operator>
		<name>k-NN Global Anomaly Score</name>
	   	<synopsis>Calculates the outlier score based on K-Nearesest-Neighbors implementation.</synopsis>
		<help> <p>
 			This operator calculates the anomaly score based on the K Nearest Neighbors
  implementation. The outlier score is by default the average of the distance
  to the nearest neighbors, it can be set to the distance to the kth nearest
  neighbor which is similar to the algorithm proposed by Ramaswamy et al (2000)
  by setting the corresponding parameter. The outlier score is calculated
  according to the measure type selected. The higher the outlier the more
  anomalous the instance is.
			</p>
		</help>	
	</operator>
	<operator>
		<name>Local Outlier Factor (LOF)</name>
	   	<synopsis>Calculates the outlier score based on Local Outlier Factor implementation, proposed 					by Breunig et al [1999; 2000].</synopsis>
		<help>	
			The LOF anomaly detection calculates the anomaly score according to the local
  			outlier factor algorithm proposed by Breunig el al.
  			
			LOF is one of the earliest local density based approaches proposed. There are several steps in the calculation of the LOF. The initial step involves getting the nearest neighbors set.The definition of the k-distance employed is the one proposed in the original paper in order to handle duplicates. The definition states that the k-distance(p)   has at least k neighbors  with distinct spatial coordinates that have a distance less than or equal it and at most k-1 of such neighbors with distance strictly less than it.  The reachability distance (reach-dist(p,o)) is the maximum of the distance between point p and o and the k-distance(o). The local reachability is the inverse of the average reachability distance over the nearest neighborhood set. Finally the LOF is   calculated as the average of the ratio of the local reachability  density over the neighborhood set. The values of the LOF oscillates with the change in the size of the neighborhood. Thus a range is defined for the size of the neighborhood. The maximum LOF over that range is taken as the final LOF score. 
 
A normal instance has an outlier value of approximately 1, while outliers have values greater than 1. 			
 
		</help>
	</operator>

	<operator>
		<name>Local Outlier Probablity (LoOP)</name>
	   	<synopsis>Calculates the outlier score based on Local outlier probablity, proposed by Kriegel et al [2009].</synopsis>
		<help>	
			LoOP score represents the probability that the object is a local density outlier. The algorithm combines the benefits of local density approaches being that it doesn't assume any distribution for the data as well as the mathematical concepts of the statistical methods. The Fact that the score is
  a probability facilitates comparisons. LoOP is also based on the nearest neighbors set. The definition of the k-distance used is the same as the one proposed by  Breunig et al [1999; 2000] to handle duplicates.
		</help>
	</operator>

	<operator>
		<name>Cluster-Based Local Outlier Factor (CBLOF)</name>
		<synopsis> Calculates the outlier score based on cluster-based local outlier factor proposed by He et al(2003)</synopsis>
		<help>	<p>
			CBLOF takes as an input the data set and the cluster model that was generated by a clustering algorithm. It  classifies the clusters into small clusters and large clusters using the parameters alpha and beta. 				The anomaly score is then calculated based on the size of the cluster the point belongs to as well as the distance to the nearest large cluster. 
			 </p>
<p> Use weighting for outlier factor based on the sizes of the clusters as proposed in the original publication. Since this might lead to unexpected behaviour (outliers close to small clusters are not found), it can be disabled and outliers scores are solely computed based on their distance to the cluster center.</p>
		</help>
	</operator>
	<operator>
		<name>Connectivity-Based Outlier Factor (COF)</name>
	   	<synopsis>Calculates the outlier score based on Connectivity Based  Outlier Factor , proposed by Tang el al(2002)</synopsis>
		<help>	<p>
			The COF is a modification of LOF algorithm (Breunig el al, 2000) proposed in order to handle outliers deviating from low density patterns. The definition of the k-distance used is the same as the one proposed by  Breunig et al [1999; 2000] to handle duplicates.he normal instances will have an outlier score of approximately 1, while outliers have a value greater than 1.  
			 </p>
		</help>
	</operator>

	<operator>
		<name>Influenced Outlierness (INFLO)</name>
	   	<synopsis>Calculates the outlier score based on Influenced outlierness , proposed by Jin et al [2006].</synopsis>
		<help>	
			The INFLO is a local density method that takes into consideration the neighbors and the reverse neighbors when estimating the local density of a given point. The algorithm is also based on the nearest neighbors set.  The definition of the k-distance used is the same as the one proposed by  Breunig et al [1999; 2000] to handle duplicates. The normal instances will have an outlier score of approximately 1, while outliers have a value greater than 1.
		</help>
	</operator>


	<operator>
		<name>Local Correlation Integeral (LOCI)</name>
	   	<synopsis>Calculates the outlier score based on The Local Correlation Integral, proposed by  Papadimitriou et al [2003].</synopsis>
		<help>	
			<p>
The algorithm has the following pros over other approaches. The results are not highly  affected by the parameters and it provides an automatic statistically intuitive cut off to determine the outliers.
</p>
<p>

The  computation of the LOCI  requires  the calculation of MDEF and &#x3C3;MDEF. MDEF  for a  point p at radius r refers to the deviation of the density of p to that in its average local neighborhood density. &#x3C3;MDEF is the normalised standard deviation of the point relative to its local neighborhood.
</p>
<p>
The original publication suggests the following flagging scheme the object should be flagged as an outlier if MDEF(p, r, &#x3B1;)&gt;  3 *&#x3C3;MDEF(p, r, &#x3B1;). The operator produces an outlier score which corresponds to the maximum ratio between MDEF(p, r, &#x3B1;) and &#x3C3;MDEF(p, r, &#x3B1;) over all r.  The higher the ratio the more outlier the object is. The proposed threshold  to determine outliers is 3.
</p> 
		</help>
	</operator>
	
    <operator>
        <name>Local Density Cluster-Based Outlier Factor (LDCOF)</name>
        <synopsis>Assigns the outlier score according to LDCOF algorithm </synopsis>
        <help>
        This is a local density based anomaly detecion algorithm. 
        The anomaly score is set to the distance to the nearest large cluster divided by the average cluster distance of the large cluster. The intuition behind this is that the small clusters are considered outlying and thus they are assigned to the nearest large cluster and this becomes its local neighborhood. The division into large and small clusters can be either done similar to what was implemented in the CBLOF paper (He et al,2003) or it can done in a manner similar to what was proposed in (Moh&#39;d Belal Al- Zoubi,2009). This is determined by the parameter &quot; divide clusters like cblof &quot;. 
        </help>
    </operator>
</operatorHelp>
